While it's true that generally an implication
and its converse are not the same thing,
they don't have the same truth value,
what you can have is a scenario where both directions,
the original conditional and it's converse,
where those are both true.
And when both of those are true,
what we can have is something called the biconditional.
And you'll notice here that in the biconditional,
it's got this sort of double-sided arrow
'cause it's saying that p implies q,
and it's the case that q implies p.
This is the idea
where p and q are sort of like equivalent properties.
If you have one, you get the other,
and if you have the other, you get the initial one.
So let's try to figure out
whether this works in terms of some statements.
If I study hard, then I will pass.
So that was the statement p implies q.
(marker squeaking)
But I can also go the other way around.
This probably applies to most of us.
I could say if I pass, then I studied hard.
So this is the statement, q implies p.
And you'll notice that
what I'm having here is if I combine these two together
and I think of them as one statement,
it's a conjunctive statement, a statement with an and in it.
It's got one implication, p implies q,
and it's got a second implication, q implies p.
And the way I should think about this is
that if we exclude people like me
or people who have a lot of familiarity with material,
they could just sort of sit down and not bother studying
at all and just pass the test already,
although truly for myself, that's just
'cause I studied a long time in the past,
if we exclude those type of cases, this is probably true.
You need to study hard in order to pass.
And if you pass, you did indeed study hard.
So both of these two different implications
are gonna be true and I can combine them
in a kind of nice way.
Look at my phraseology here.
I say I will pass
and I use this funny word, funny phrase,
if and only if I study hard.
So whenever we write that,
whenever we say this sort of if and only if thing here,
this is a way of saying
that both directions are gonna be true.
It's a way of saying if I study hard, then I will pass.
And if I passed, then I studied hard.
That's what I have here.
The first of these ifs is referring
to the stop statement and the second of them,
the one that says only if is referring
to the other way around, the if I pass, then I studied hard.
So mathematicians really like this phrase,
this if and only if as sort of a shorthand
for talking about biconditionals,
as a shorthand for having a conjunctive statement
with two different conditionals written down.
They just put if one thing,
this is the passing the thing I want to have,
that's gonna be true if and only if I study hard.